name I pray. Amen. Well, thanks again for joining us. If we haven't had the privilege
of meeting yet, my name is Ryan, and I truly have, I truly count it as an honor to be one
of the pastors of this church. So excited to see what God has been doing in our church
over the last two years. Some really exciting things have been happening the last few weeks
and the few months. We've been experiencing a lot of growth and seeing a lot of cool things
that God is doing in the lives of people. And so I'm just so grateful to be a part of
that. We just wrapped up last week, a series where we were doing some frequently asked questions
and I had about one week, not about one week. Oh, am I going to, I'm not going to be on the
screen the whole time, am I? That's going to, you guys do you, but that, that'll be a bit
of a distraction. Uh, we got one week until we turn our eyes to Advent. And so, um, as
we were talking with people, as I was talking with people about this idea of rededication,
I was just kept being drawn to this passage in Matthew chapter seven. So I want to spend
a week on that and then we'll turn our eyes to Advent. And if you're new here, I want to
let you know, there's a lot of you that are newer here. And so at the end of January, just
go ahead and plan this. Think about this at the end of January, we're going to have a
two week class, uh, the last two Sundays in January. For those of you that are newer,
that want to learn more about our church, want to ask me questions, want to get more
involved. Um, we call that our C3 connection class. And so we'd love to have you plan for
that at the end of January. All right. So if you want to turn in your Bibles, we're going
to be in Matthew chapter seven. And before we get there as a pastor, I am a student of
effective preaching. Um, I love to think about preaching. I love to interact with
content about preaching. Um, it can be helpful. It also can be really difficult because every
time I listened to a sermon, I struggle to actually listen to the sermon. I'm like thinking
about the outline and where is this person headed? Where are they taking us? Where are
they going to land the plane? I'm constantly breaking down the structure and anticipating
the direction. And what I've learned throughout the years is that all good preaching, the best
preaching is aimed at clear and compelling application. It's aimed at inviting us to do something with
the truth that we're interacting with. Preaching isn't primarily about teaching new information,
but about inviting people to put that information into practice. And, um, as a college student,
I remember I attended a winter retreat as a leader, which I never should have been a leader.
You don't let 19 year old boys be in charge of anything. Um, but I was honored to be a part
of this, uh, winter retreat. And the speaker that weekend was one of the best preachers I
had ever heard. Communicators that I'd ever heard. His sermons, his sermons were clear
and compelling. He had a bold delivery and, um, the application had layered nuance. It had
far reaching implications for the entire audience. And I remember picking his brain after that
winter retreat because I was a new preacher and was not good. Um, I'm a little better now, but still,
so you guys know, you've got to persevere through some of this stuff. I picked his brain
and his application in particular was always just incredible. And I said, how do you like,
how do you land the plane so well? How do you make everything so applicable to everybody in the room?
And he said, I'll never forget it. He said, I spend one hour in prayer and meditation for every
age demographic in the room. One hour for sixth grade girls, one hour for sixth grade boys,
one hour for seventh grade girl. Like all, like, I'm just like, how does this message apply to this
particular age group, this particular demographic? I do not do that. In case you're wondering, you guys
pay me too much, not enough. I don't know. But I remember like, it just stuck with me. Like everything
about his message was about how does this apply to each specific person in the room.
And, um, I'm not sure what we're going to do today is that in Matthew chapter seven, we're actually going to
look at the application, the main application of one of Jesus's most primary sermons, the sermon on the
mount. And when we get to the end, we're going to find that because he's probably the best preacher that
ever lived that his, his message is application is clear and compelling. His delivery is bold and it
has far reaching implications for the entire audience. Now, I don't know if Jesus spent an hour
in prayer and meditation for every single age demographic in his, um, crowd, but I do know that
he had the privilege of like knowing their hearts and minds. So he probably spent some time praying,
but he also knew what they were thinking that probably helped. Um, and so what I want to do
today is I want to look at Jesus's application to one of his most primary sermons. We're going to
break it down with those three sections. It's first is it's, it's clear and compelling. And if you have
your bulletins and you want to follow along, I do have some fill in the blank notes on the back.
Um, that is for those of you that are type a people. And for those of you that want to know how
close I am to being done, um, that works for both of you. So feel free to follow along. We're going to
look at the, the clear and compelling nature of Jesus's application to bold delivery. And at the
end, we're going to look at the far reaching implications of the sermon. So let's read it
again. Um, Matthew chapter seven, verse 24 says, everyone then who hears these words of mine and does
them will be like a wise man who built his house on the rock. The rain fell and the floods came and the
winds blew and beat on that house, but it did not fall because it had been founded on the rock.
And everyone who hears these words of mine and does not do them will be like a foolish man
who built his house on the sand and the rain fell and the floods came and the winds blew and beat against
that house. And it fell and great was the fall of it. It's the end of one of Jesus's most primary
sermons. And this is the crowd's response. And when Jesus had finished, finished these things, the crowds
were astonished at his teaching for he was teaching them as one who had authority.
So this is one of the most clear and compelling teachings of Jesus that you will ever interact with.
If I were bold enough to give Jesus some tips on preaching, um, I would say that he has the tendency
of being a, being a bit cryptic from time to time. Anybody eat my flesh, drink my blood. What are you
saying? Like at times Jesus is intentionally cryptic. He's intentionally vague. He's intentionally
open ended, but not here at the end of this message. It is very clear and compelling. I would say it's
probably the most clear that Jesus will be when he teaches his followers. The message is easy to
understand. He has two hypothetical people. Both listen to the teachings of Jesus. One of them obeys
and is called wise. The other disobeys and is called a fool. The wise person is able to persevere any
difficult circumstances in their life while the foolish person's house crashes when the difficulty
comes. Now I'm not going to spend a ton of time unpacking what all of this means, because I think
it's pretty simple to understand. It's pretty clear cut, but I do want to zoom in on one or two important
things. And the first is that both hypothetical individuals hear the word of God. One applies and one
doesn't. It does not say one agrees with and one is offended. One believes and one rejects. We could
assume here that both hypothetical people listen to the teaching of Jesus and affirm it, agree with it,
say this is a good thing, but one person applies it and the other person just listens to it. I think this
is important because I think if we're honest, many of us who have grown up in the church, who have spent a lot
of time in the church, we fall into a category of person who regularly listens to and believes in the
teachings of Jesus. But what about application? Are we a people that build our lives on obedience to the
teachings of Jesus or just belief in an agreement with the teachings of Jesus? Because Jesus seems to call
that type of person a fool. I think the American church tends to emphasize learning more and agreeing
with what Jesus teaches over and above the applications of his teachings. We get fixated on learning more,
understanding more. It's the very Western cultural ideology. Like we just want to know more. We want
to understand more. We want to have every question answered. And I think sometimes we spend so much
time trying to answer every potential question that we could ever have about our faith that when it
comes to actually doing the basic things that Jesus tells us to do, like loving our neighbors as
ourselves. We're like, I got to go. I got to read another Bible study on that before I do it. I got
to memorize another passage of Scripture before I do it. It's clear here that Jesus isn't saying one
believes and one doesn't believe. He's saying one obeys and one doesn't obey. And so my question for us
this morning as we interact with the teachings of Jesus is, are we a people who are building our life
on obedience to Jesus or just agreeing with Jesus?
If you're following in the notes, my first point is this information without application leads to
stagnation. It's like reading a book about weightlifting and expecting for your muscles to get bigger.
Right? Like if you're like, I want to get in shape, I'm going to get a couple books. It's going to be
great. I'm going to read the books. I'm going to learn about what it would take in order to be in
shape. And then all of a sudden, bang, pow, magic muscles. Right? That was not in my notes. I don't
know what just happened there. Dave cut the last stream. No, I'm just kidding. Now I'm not saying that
learning more is bad. I love to read and understand more of the depth of Christ's teaching. But if we're
constantly adding study guides, reading plans, and classes into our life with no real life change,
we are on a very unhealthy trajectory. Someone might even say that we are building our house on sand.
Information without application leads to stagnation. But on the other hand, information with application
leads to transformation. Our lives are transformed from the inside out, not purely through learning more
about Jesus, but through following his example and putting his words into practice. We are not conformed
to his image primarily through study, but through service.
The last point I want to make here on this section is that both hypothetical people build a house.
Building a house is not an easy thing. Some of you are building a house right now. It's not an easy
thing, right? So both people are doing something. They are building a house. And the crazy thing about a
house on a rock versus a house on the sand is when there are no storms,
they both look the same, right? Both houses are stable. Both houses are sturdy. Both houses are doing what they
were intended to do. But it's when the storm comes where you find out whether the house was built on
the sand or built on the rock. And I don't know much about building houses. Actually, I know next to
nothing about building houses. But I assume that building a house on sand is easier in the moment
than building a house on rock. And I think, I think that maybe this is part of the reason American
Christianity is so obsessed with learning more information, because I don't know about you, but I
think sitting through a Bible study and learning more information is a lot easier than actually loving
our neighbor as ourselves. So we do this version of Christianity that's easier than the version of
Christianity that Jesus is inviting us into. We do this version of Christianity that's built on learning
more information and not actually putting that information in to practice. I know a lot of
Christians who look like they've got it all together. They can quote Scripture inside and out.
They can talk about all of their systematic theological frameworks, but I've been pastoring long
enough to know to see people who look like they've got it all together face a storm in their life
and their house comes crashing down. And on the other side of the coin, I know people who cannot spell
theology. That one was, come on people. I was waiting for that one. I know, I know people literally who
can't spell theology, but they do the stuff they submit to Jesus daily in their lives and they might
not have all of the right words or verbiage or terminology to make you think that they're a strong
Christian. But when the winds come and the storms blow their house remains standing because their house
is built on faith in and obedience to Jesus, not just information about Jesus.
It's a pretty simple, clear message here. Jesus isn't pulling any punches. Listen and obey and you are wise.
Listen and agree.
You're foolish.
Are we a people
who build our life on a faith in and obedience to Jesus or are we a people
who build our life on listening to and agreeing with
what Jesus has to say?
This message is clear and compelling.
His delivery is bold.
Verse 28,
When he finished these things, the crowds were astonished at his teachings for he was teaching
them as one who had authority, not as the scribes.
Jesus' delivery of this message was far different than any message that they had ever heard.
Because every message that they had heard up to this point
had been, this is what the Bible says.
This is what the word of God says.
This is how I interpret it.
I invite you to
follow in my interpretation.
And Jesus isn't doing that at all.
He is speaking as if the words that he is saying are coming from God
himself.
This is different.
Altogether different.
In a podcast I listened to this week from Tim Mackey, he points out that Christ's language
in the application of this sermon is very similar to Moses' language at the end of his giving
of the law in Deuteronomy 31.
The verbiage is very similar to Moses in Deuteronomy.
It's very similar to King Solomon in Proverbs chapter 1.
And the point that Tim made in that section is he's saying what Christ is doing to the original
audiences, he is hinting to them that I am the greater lawgiver than Moses, I am the greater
king, and I have the greater wisdom than King Solomon, the greatest king that we've ever had,
one of the greatest kings that we've ever had.
Jesus is very clearly drawing a line in the sand and saying I'm not another prophet, I'm not
another teacher, I am God.
He's signaling, he's a different kind of teacher.
He's not just teaching us God's word on behalf of God, he is teaching in a way that lines up
with the claims about himself, he is God.
He isn't just inviting you to submit to morality, but to submit your lives to his leadership.
I think this is in the notes.
This is why the people were amazed at the end of his sermon.
They understood what he was saying.
Now, I point this out because I think there are some of us in the room,
some of us in American Christianity as a whole, that were really drawn to the moral teachings of Jesus.
We love the idea of the teachings of Jesus, love you neighbor as yourself.
We love all of the stuff that he has to say.
We love the way that he treats the sinner.
We love the way that he says, those of you who haven't sinned, you cast the first stone, right?
Like, we love this non-judgmental, loving version of Jesus.
But I think it's important to point out here that Jesus isn't asking us to submit our lives to his moral teachings.
He's asking us to submit our lives to his leadership.
He is the king and ruler of our lives.
Maybe you're here and you appreciate his moral teachings, but you're not really sure if he is who he says he is.
It's a good starting point.
But if that's your conclusion, you will miss the entire point of Christ's teaching.
C.S. Lewis has a famous framework where he kind of pokes a hole in this idea.
Because some of you have probably heard this.
He says, Jesus is either Lord, a lunatic, or a liar.
He can't just be a good moral teacher, because if he's just a good moral teacher, he's claiming that he is God in the flesh.
So he either has to be a liar, he has to be nuts, or he has to be who he says he is.
And so if there's some of us in the room that we just really like the idea of Jesus' teachings, we think he's a good moral leader, a good moral teacher.
No, that is not what he is claiming to be.
And the crowd knew it, and they were astonished.
I think this one's in the notes.
It says this, we must allow the application of this message to confront our lives, not as a moral teacher trying to persuade us to live righteous lives.
That is not Jesus' goal.
But as the king of the universe with all the wisdom that exists, inviting us to be a part of his one true kingdom.
Jesus' message is clear and compelling.
It is bold in delivery, and it has far-reaching implications for our lives.
Although it is clear on the surface, I think there's layers to this application.
I think if we're going to get the nuance of the application that Jesus is making, we've got to ask ourselves, what are the storms, and what or who is the house?
And it might seem like that's an easy enough question to answer, but I think it's a bit more nuanced than we might think.
So let's start with, what are the storms of our lives that Jesus is referring to?
I think there, based on my study, I think there's three different types of storms that Jesus might have in mind in his giving of this message.
I have been doing, believe it or not, I feel far away from you all.
I'm feeling brave.
Believe it or not, I am trying hard to shorten my sermons.
And this week, I was like, you know what?
I have too much content.
So I did something.
We're going to cover two of the three storms.
And one of the storms, I recorded a short video.
We're going to put it in the newsletter.
So if you want bonus content, come back for more.
Join the newsletter.
This is dangerous.
But for now, we're just going to cover two of the three storms so that I finish on time.
Sound good?
All right.
The first.
Somebody's like, no, keep going.
I heard you guys after Corey's message last week.
I know you don't mean it.
The first type of storm that I think Jesus has in mind is individual storms.
Individual storms.
Storms that impact us personally.
And even in that type of storm, there's two versions of this type of storm.
Proverbs chapter 26, verse 27 says, whoever digs a pit will fall into it.
If someone rolls a stone, it will roll back on them.
And what Solomon is saying here is if you do, if you make enough decisions where you're trying to take advantage of people by digging holes for them to fall into, eventually you will fall into your own hole.
And I think what Jesus is saying here is if we reject his teachings, if we reject his authority in our lives, we will end up making a pattern of destructive decisions that will lead to storms in our own life.
We can create storms in our life by disobedience to the teachings of Jesus, by not submitting to the authority of Jesus.
We lie, we steal, we cheat, we gossip, we self-medicate, and we lust to get what we want in the moment.
And it will eventually catch up to us.
If you refuse to obey the teachings of Jesus, eventually you will bring about storms in your life from the decisions that you make.
Many of us in the room this morning know this all too well.
Many of us in here have experienced the crushing blow of storms in our life.
And we know when we lay our head down on the pillow at night, we know that those storms were caused by our own decisions.
The decisions that we made, the pattern of unchecked sin, of refusal to confess, of refusal to repent.
We have created storms in our life.
Those storms have impacted those around us because of the decisions that we have made.
Not only are some of us in the room here and have already faced the storms of life that we caused by the decisions that we make,
but I believe God sent me here this morning to tell some of you,
you are on a pattern of decision-making that will create a storm,
that will bring your house crashing down.
Some of you have patterns of unchecked sin, things that you're hiding, things that you're not being honest about.
You're presenting yourself to your family, to your friends, and to your church as something that you are not.
And I believe God wants me to warn you that today, it's not too late.
You have an opportunity now to come clean, to confess, to be honest, to be open about the things that you've done,
and to receive God's healing and his mercy and his forgiveness.
And those of you that have created storms in your life because of decisions that you have made,
you do not have to stay there in shame or regret or guilt.
You can pick yourself up.
You can seek repentance and forgiveness from God.
You can do what you need to do to get yourself straight, to get out of the patterns and decisions that you've made.
You can go to the people that you have hurt, and you can seek forgiveness and reconciliation.
And whether or not they receive that repentance, whether or not they extend you forgiveness,
just know that God and Christ has forgiven you.
And you can't control their response.
All you can control is what you do with the decisions that you've made.
We can avoid some storms in our life if we get serious about obeying the teachings of Jesus.
The good news is that there is healing, forgiveness, and restoration through Jesus.
Don't stay in the pit.
Receive his grace and his forgiveness.
The second version of individual storms, you might have guessed,
are storms that happen to you because of decisions that others have made.
This is the most devastating type of storm because often you had no control over it whatsoever.
A loved one, a father, a mother, a husband, a wife, a friend betrayed you, lied to you.
They presented to you something that wasn't true.
And eventually the truth came out.
We cannot avoid these storms, but we can lessen their impact by building our life on the rock,
by having eternal perspective.
The decisions of others, listen to me.
For those of you that have experienced pain, for those of you that have been abused,
for those of you that have been taken advantage of by those who are supposed to keep you safe,
for those of you that have had storms come to your life because of decisions that others have made on you,
hear this.
The decisions of others do not have to define you.
Your identity is not found in the decision of others, but in what God says about you.
Extend forgiveness, turn the other cheek, trust in God who is the eternal and just judge who will wipe away every tear from our eyes.
If someone, if you're experiencing storms that have been caused by others, don't allow them to have that much power over your life.
Go to the Lord and receive his healing and redemptive power.
There's individual storms.
There's corporate storms that we don't have time to go over.
So subscribe to the newsletter.
It's almost like I went to, they should call Bible college marketing school.
Just like a cheap version, bad marketing school.
Okay.
Last type of storm is the cosmic storm, the ultimate storm that is coming for all of us, no matter how we live.
Death and the grave is on the horizon of all of us.
Death has a 100% satisfaction guarantee rate, right?
There's no avoiding it.
And yet Jesus seems to say that there's a way that we can live.
There's a way we can build our lives that will allow us to persevere even death and the grave itself.
Which leads us to our last question.
Who or what is the rock?
Anybody who was a A plus Sunday school student want to yell out what they think the answer to this question might be?
Yeah, there we go.
Jesus is the rock.
In the Old Testament, the rock is thought of as the temple of Jerusalem sitting on top of the rock.
All who would build their lives in genuine obedience to and worship to the one true God would persevere.
Wow, that one's a hard one.
Any storm they might face.
But now as we turn our eyes to Jesus in the New Testament, he will go on to say, tear the temple down and I will rebuild it in three days.
Obviously, in hindsight, that's referring to his death and resurrection.
The life, the victory and the teachings of Jesus become the one true rock that if we build our lives on, faith in him and obedience to his teachings, we will be able to weather any storm.
Even the storm of death itself.
And his resurrection proves this.
I said it was a 100% satisfaction guarantee except for one time in human history.
And that is the reason that you and I are here because Jesus did die.
He was buried and he did raise from the dead.
And if he didn't, we're wasting our time.
But if he did, building our house on faith in him and obedience to his teachings will allow us to persevere even the cosmic storm of death itself.
Tim Mackey says it this way.
Jesus becomes the first one whose house on a rock withstands the flood.
He goes through the storm for us.
He weathers the storm of decisions of others.
Think about it.
Jesus, as he's going to the cross, he's weathering the storm of the decision of Judas to betray him.
Of the decision of Pilate to not stand up for what's right, but to just give the people what they want.
Of the decisions of the nation of Israel who have rejected their Messiah and said, give us Barabbas.
Jesus is weathering the storms of decisions that other people have made.
He is setting an example for us, trusting himself to the Lord who judges justly.
And he goes to the cross and the very people that are mocking him and spitting him in his face.
He says, Father, forgive them for they do not know what they are doing.
He dies and they think they've had victory.
They think some lunatic or liar has died.
And finally, we're done with him.
But three days later, he raises from the grave, proving that he has had victory over sin, death, and the grave.
He becomes the first one whose house on a rock withstands the flood of death itself.
And if we want to persevere the storms of death and the storms of death, we do so not by just thinking positive thoughts about Jesus's life, but by faith in and obedience to his teachings.
All right.
So, as we wrap up, the question that I was thinking for myself this week, and band, you all can come up and prepare to kind of lead us in this concluding part.
I was thinking to myself, I'm preaching a message on the application, the conclusion, the application of one of the best sermons Jesus has ever preached.
How can I write an application about the application of one of Jesus's best sermons he's ever preached?
I decided that the only move here is to steal a play out of Jesus's playbook and just ask you all a bunch of questions.
I love that.
I love when Jesus, somebody asks Jesus a question and then he answers with a question.
So, you might be thinking, what do I do with this message?
Well, let me respond to you with some questions.
First, is your discipleship to Jesus more focused on learning information or applying information?
When you interact with the Scriptures, when you interact with other people about the Bible and Jesus, when you come to church or go to a passages class or join a small group,
are you focused more on learning more information or doing what Jesus invites you to do?
Do you believe that Jesus has the authority to command the direction of your entire life?
And if you would answer yes to that question, do your daily decisions reflect the answer to that question?
Or are there certain areas in our life that we're like, yeah, he has the authority over most of my life, but not this part, not right now.
Maybe later, once I get all the things I want out of this relationship or this pattern of sin,
maybe one day I will hand it over to the Lord.
Have decisions you've made contributed to the storms of your life?
Are there storms that you're facing and that others in your orbit are facing because of decisions that you made, patterns of sin that you participated in?
A lack of repentance, a lack of confession.
Did you allow yourself to get so far down a path that you fell into a hole and brought other people with you?
If that's you, what can you do to make an effort to calm those storms?
If you're in here and the storms of your life have been created by others and the decisions that others have made,
I'd ask you this question, are you allowing the decisions of others to have too much power over your life?
What can you do to release some of the weight of the decisions that others have made and give them to God,
building your house on his rock?
Are you building your life around faith in and obedience to Jesus in a way that will allow you to persevere inevitable storms of life and death?
Today, I wanted to provide an opportunity to encourage those of us who are in the building, who we're building, we know, we know.
We're not perfect, but we're building our life on the rock.
I want to encourage you.
If you're in here and you're like, yes, that's me.
I am building my life on the rock.
I'm not perfect.
I'm not doing everything great, but I'm trying by faith and trust in the Holy Spirit.
I just want to encourage you today.
I know it's hard.
I know it'd be a lot easier to build your life on sand, but it's worth it.
Your life will persevere any storm that you face if you continue to submit your life to faith in and obedience to Jesus.
Be encouraged.
The storms will come, but your life will persevere.
The second group are those of you that know in the past you've made a decision to build your life on the rock.
Maybe you went into the waters of baptism.
You've made that decision and you were following for a while.
But at this moment in time, you look back at your life and you say, there's a trajectory of my life that's been leading me away.
I started on the rock and now I'm building on top of that rock with sand.
I just wanted to provide an opportunity for people to just set up a monument.
I got a bucket full of rocks up here and some Sharpies.
I just want those of us that are thinking, yeah, that's me.
I've made a decision at one point, but, and you can define what that means for you.
Maybe you're way off track or maybe you're just a little bit off track,
but you know that today is a day for you to make a decision.
I'm going to stop the trajectory of my life that is leading me away from the rock.
And I'm coming back.
I'm resubmitting my life to Jesus this morning.
If that's you, I want to invite you here in a minute.
We're going to sing.
And I'd love to invite anybody that's here and that's feeling that way to come up and grab a rock.
There's Sharpies, write the date, write whatever it is that the Lord's leading you to do.
Think about this and take this rock home and carry it with you and put it somewhere you can see it and remind yourself.
I'm choosing today to continue to build my life on the rock.
And maybe you're in here and you've never made this decision.
I want you to also have the opportunity for the first time ever to come up and grab a rock.
I said it earlier, but the nation of Israel would often set up monuments for themselves.
Actually, God would ask them to set up monuments for themselves.
Any guesses on why God would ask them to set up monuments for themselves?
They are prone to wander.
Lord, I feel it.
Just read the Old Testament.
The nation of Israel is prone to wander.
We are a people who are prone to forget decisions that we've made.
We're prone to be distracted and led astray by the enemy, the world, the flesh, and the devil.
And so maybe you're here and you've never made a decision to follow Jesus before.
I hope that I did a good enough job of staying out of the way of one of the best applications of the best sermon
that you'll ever hear.
If you build your life on the faith in and obedience to Jesus' teaching,
you will persevere any storm that you face.
So if you're here and you want to decide for the first time to follow Jesus,
we'd love to have you come up, grab a rock, grab a Sharpie,
take whatever time you need.
For the rest of us, let's be in prayer and in worship
as the band leads us in one final song.
We'll see you next time.